for
for e
for for
good morning everyone good morning
morning
morning all right um we are now in
session in the matter of DPW Enterprises
LLC in Mountain Prime 2018 LC versus
Jeremy bass and Dwayne Pike this is case
number CV 35-
24-10
63 we have a present on behalf of uh
excuse me uh DPW plaintiff in this
matter is L Stoddard um appearing by uh
video on the zoom session present on
behalf of uh Dwayne Pike is his attorney
keni I think I see Mr Pike there in the
background yes your honor he's here with
me all right and also present is uh by
video is Jeremy bass um representing
himself and this matter was set for
hearing today on the plaintiff's motion
for summary
judgment in this
matter the motion for summary judgment
along with the memorandum and three
declarations was filed back on September
16 was originally set for hearing on the
15th and then uh reset to the 22nd I
believe to accommodate Mr Nei schedule
and then on October 1st of 24 uh Mr Nei
on behalf of Mr Pike filed his response
and supporting affa
davit um on October 8th Mr Bass asked
for this matter to be
continued as he indicated he had more
needed more time to respond uh there was
a compromise uh through that hearing
that um where the plaintiff agreed to
allow Mr Bass an additional week to file
his response and they uh and expedite
their reply so Mr Bass was given until
October 15 to file his response and
plaintiff was giving until October 18 to
file a reply on October 14 plaintiff
filed their reply to uh defendant Pike's
um response October 15 Mr Bass filed his
response and affidavit and submitted a
thumb drive as well and then on October
18th uh plain us filed their reply and
affidavit to um Mr bass's
response and then late yesterday
afternoon Mr Bass filed
three I guess he calls them responses to
a portion of the
reply um there is no provision for there
to be a reply to a reply and the state
or excuse me and the court is not going
to consider the three documents filed by
Mr Bass yesterday afternoon at 4:41
and so with that um Mr Stoddard uh this
is your motion so I'll hear argument
from you
first thank you honor um as the court is
aware the record before this court this
is a standard post forclosure action for
a ejectment uh there are two defendants
each with differing postures in this
matter the first is Mr Bass who occupies
the property as the former owner uh of
that property uh and then Mr Pike is the
only other defendant who has appeared uh
who is asserting that he is a tenant of
the property uh and entitled to remain
in that property pursuant to a executive
lease agreement um because the I guess
the analysis with respect to each of
them differs I'll take each one
separately but uh the case law is clear
your honor that following a non-judicial
foreclosure uh the successful purchaser
is entitled to possession 10 days
following that sale uh the Undisputed
record before the court uh indicates
that there was a default on Adida trust
for Mr Bass sign uh that encumbered the
real property um that a sale was noticed
subsequently postponed multiple times
litigation uh took place between Mr Bass
and the trustee and
beneficiary um that was dismissed and
ultimately a a trustee sale was
conducted was held on the courthouse
steps uh and a representative of my
clients attended that sale uh submitted
the winning bid a trustees deed was
issued and reported uh in its favor so
plaintiffs at this point are making a
claim to to have possession of that
property as against the interest of Mr
Bass and Mr Pike because they purchased
it at a successful Trustee of sale um
the consequences of a trustee sale with
respect to a former borrower are clear
it terminates all right title and
interest of that former borrower and
again uh they were entitled to
possession 10 days following that sale
Mr Bass still maintains possession of
the sale adds evidence by his pleadings
he is refusing to relinquish possession
um he has presented no evidence
indicating any irregularity with the way
that the sale was conducted by way of
notice or any other statutory
irregularity rather what Mr Bass has set
forth before the court is the number of
conclusory
I'll call him conspiracy theories as to
what he think occurred can I object to
that um it's all
speculation uh the record before the
court including Mr bass's own evidence
reflects that there was a sale held it
was held outside anybody could attend um
he hasn't presented any evidence that
people were uh stopped from attending
that sale that people were told not to
come to the sale that people were
somehow um scared away from that sale
and in fact Mr Bat is seen in those
videos that the court reviewed them
holding a sign intended to dissuade
people from attending that sale uh
giving some sort of indication that they
might be subject to criminal penalties
or or jail time
um really at the end of the day with
respect to Mr
bass's uh right to possession of that
property he hasn't presented the court
with any evidence indicating any
statutory failure in the non-judicial
foreclosure process
uh and in fact the trustees deed is
entitled for Prima fascia um presumption
of compliance uh and the recital therein
are entitled to a primacia presumption
of of uh of truth that includes that a
notice of default was given recorded
that the various statutory notices were
given uh that would include posting that
would include mailing Mr Bass attended
the sale and therefore the records clear
that he had actual notice of the sale in
the law in Idaho it's clear that where
there are no issues regarding the
statutory notice Provisions that trustee
sale becomes uh final um Mr Bass has
raised a number of questions regarding
how the sale is conducted and again um
is alleging that there was some form of
collusion but cites no Cas support for
those propositions uh rather my client
contacted the trustee in advance of the
sale to find out what the opening credit
bid was going to be
credit bids have been acknowledged by
the Ido Supreme Court as proper uh bid
bidding procedures for a
creditor uh having found out what the um
opening bid amount was going to be and
how those funds needed to be tendered my
client sent its own representative to
that sale did on its behalf where it was
the successful purchaser placing the
highest bid and thus the property was
sold to it that nobody else showed up to
the sale I don't know why that would
have occurred neither does Mr Bass and
so there is no evidence in the record
that bids again didn't attend because of
some I guess alleged collusion or or
other um price fixing or whatever Mr
Bass wants to allege um and so for that
reason your honor um I think the record
is clear that uh my clients are entitled
possession immediate possession of that
property as against any interest uh
claimed by Mr
B um with respect to Mr Pikes the
analysis changes a bit Mr Pike uh is
apparently a tenant of that
property um following the sale as is
common practice in my practice we send a
notice to vacate to the property the
purpose of that notice to vacate is to
let former owners like Mr Bass know that
hey the property was sold uh you need to
vacate that property but also with
respect to tenants who we may or may not
know about it is to inform the tenants
of potential they might have under the
detecting tenant the Foreclosure act uh
the notice to vacate that was sent uh Mr
Pike received he called my office um at
that point he said I'm here on a
month-to month lease I'm entitled to 90
days to
vacate no disagreement there uh that's
with the protecting tenant foreclosure
act affords a tenant that's there on a
month-to Monon
leas ultimately it didn't make any sense
to to initiate two separate I and so Mr
Baff and Mr Pike both got the benefit of
90 days uh to vacate the property and
when they failed to uh the complaint for
ejectment was
filed uh in responding to the complaint
for ejectment for the first time Mr Pike
uh filed a reported two-year lead
renewal entered in prior to the
Foreclosure sale um I attempted to try
and negotiate with with Mr ngi on behalf
of Mr Pike uh but when negotiations
ultimately failed your your honor I'm
going to object to any discussion uh
regarding settlement
negotiations I I don't intend to discuss
the terms your honor just that we had we
we
communicated um ultimately when the
matter couldn't be resolved amicably it
became necessary to to file the joint
motion for summary judgment as against
both
individuals uh the short of the summary
judgment as against Mr Pike is that if
he is there pursuing to aaf
uh he needs to prove that he's in
compliance with that lead and in fact
the notice to vacate that was given to
Mr Pike said if you believe you're a
Bonafide tenant provide a copy of the
leas so we can evaluate it determine if
you're there if you're uh pursuant to a
month the month or for a term uh give us
copies of your previous rent payments so
we can determine that you're in
compliance with your lead uh and most
importantly and I think the issue before
this cour is you need to continue to
make your lease of payments if you're
there underneath the Bonafide
lease um the record before the coure in
the Undisputed evidence is that Mr Pike
uh failed to do any of
that uh at least with respect to my
client he was informed that my clients
purchased the property he was informed
and asked to send my clients a copy of
any lease agreement so they could
evaluate it he was informed and asked to
continue to make payments uh under that
leads agreement to my clients as the new
owners uh none of that occurred uh
rather the Undisputed fact before the
court is that Mr Pike elected to
continue making his rent payments to Mr
Bass uh and unfortunately that he chose
to pay the wrong individual his rent for
the preceding seven
months uh does not render him in
compliance with that leas agreement
especially where he seeks to have my
clients Bound by the terms of that leas
agreement uh in so for that reason uh
your
honor uh Mr Pike's attempt to avoid uh
removal from the property pursuant to a
lease agreement also fails because he is
not in compliance with that leas
agreement has not paid rent to my
clients during intervening seven months
continues to not pay rent for my clients
but is instead elected to pay Mr Bass
who has no right title or interest in
that property and so uh again I think uh
um the case law on that entitles my
client to immediate possession of of the
property and with that if there's no
other no questions or if the court has
questions I'm happy to respond I don't
have questions at this at this time Mr
Stoddard so let's take up a response to
each of those we'll start with the first
argument was in regards to Mr Bass so Mr
Bass would you like to respond to that
uh yeah by their own filing uh the
second Declaration of DPW Enterprises um
it is mentioned that they had contacted
the trustees that is a violation of the
Sherman Act um that is not upheld by any
court that you're allowed to which is
proofed by by the fact that you put the
number the payoff amount in the
notice um that right there takes it out
of uh as as I understand it would cause
a jurisdictional problem because uh
Federal uh statutes would be adjudicated
in uh federal court not in District
Court
um
the as I stated before in uh uh earlier
CA earlier hearings um I was instructed
to stay in the property by uh the
Prosecuting Office uh that there's open
investigations occurring and as far as I
understand are still occurring and uh I
was uh told by uh John uh or I'm sorry
uh Nathan Nathaniel Rudd from the
prosecutor's office to uh sit tight and
stay in my house um until there's a case
that crosses his
desk um as far as the
uh
the lease goes um if for whatever reason
uh uh I was to be found not the owner
um Mr Pike has paid his rent uh to me as
far as he understands there's be as far
as as as I understand it um there's no
reason for him to believe that there was
any other owner because we got in
complete uh uh notices that were missing
pieces and that would be uh for the the
plaintiff to go ahead and prove uh that
they had sent uh the notices uh
incomplete form and uh correct uh
otherwise we would have no reason to uh
to buy by them because why would we
believe that that was if it's uh
incomplete it could be anyone that could
send that
um for uh also to point is that in order
for to have rent uh or to have a tenant
you have to have the house at 68 degrees
you have to have uh things electricity
on things like that and there was no
attempt by anyone to uh to take those
and and make sure that Mr Pike was taken
care of correctly and had his rights uh
as a tenant were
maintained um I paid those and just as I
paid the uh taxes and the insurance
which was part of the uh verbal
agreement that I had with uh Caron
mortgage that's uh that I have
both the uh recorded uh conversation
from Miss uh Morin uh claiming that she
was talking with the the trustees or uh
the bank and that uh Mr uh uh wangs or
Wang's guard also agreed uh that he had
talked to the trustees before um I think
it's uh very clear that that they had
had been in communication and any
communication with them would be
uh in question of whether it' be uh
price fixing or not I mean you could you
could easily just go uh no you don't
really want to buy that and leave it at
that um or yeah you know congratulations
that's going to be a great buy anything
that's positive or negative uh even if
it's just giving the number would still
be uh uh price fixing uh because you're
steering the the customer or the biders
away and which is the legislative intent
of why the number is included in the
notice
um uh see and then
uh uh my attendance to the uh to the to
the auction uh I was prevented from
bidding because they had already
uh had already price fixed it that they
had
arrangements and because I was prevented
from it I couldn't make a bid because I
would be
knowingly uh participating in a fixed
auction which would made me party to
that uh so I was prevented from bidding
from on the house and
uh
uh there's no
um sorry uh
sorry
I'm reading my notes
um as far as the uh the awareness of
property defects uh beforehand the
uh it is assumed uh in the in the
statutes that you are you have a due
diligence to to look at the properties
uh and if they talked to the trustee uh
the trustee would have been able to tell
them uh very clearly that there was
issues because I've made it very clearly
very clear to the trustees that there
was problems so since they had called uh
and and got a number they should have
been uh aware of the issues which makes
them a non- Bonafide buyer uh in that
sense right there so the fact that they
called them uh takes them completely out
of the realm of uh protection from the
status of a bonafied
buyer uh because they had all rights and
all ability uh to uh find out
information about the property before
paying for it and which makes them
knowingly participating in uh this with
all those
problems uh these
are uh I had provided the uh evidence of
the of talk with the trustees in the
filings from yesterday I understand that
the court does not want to uh take them
um are they are we allowed to have the
evidence put
in uh without
the the Declarations or the
responses what do you mean the attached
to each one of those there was uh proof
so um as far as like the allegation of
uh me Mis misquoting things on purpose
um I included a shepherd's report that
uh showed that the plaintiff side had uh
more errors in theirs more citation
errors than mine um and uh part of that
evidence was also that uh there was a uh
the emails that had been uh sent to the
trustees that made them very aware that
uh that there was problems with the the
property and so by them Comm
communicating with the trustees it would
assume it would be assumed that uh that
they would have been aware of the issues
let me interrupt for a moment Mr Bass
when you say that there were problems
with the property what are you referring
to was there was the property run down
what what are there issues with the uh
there's several I don't know there's
several issues with the property uh with
the both the title and the property
itself of what they were trying to sell
uh with the propi with the title is what
you're talking about uh yes and and with
the physical defects to the property uh
the physical defects with the property
are are separate uh but there are
defects that were that are there um that
the buyer would have been known claiming
let me just want I just want to clear
what your argument is because sometimes
I can't follow you your argument is that
it was on the because the trustees were
made aware by you in emails that you
sent to the trustees that you claim an
issue with the
title that the buyer in this case the
plaintiff should have been aware of
those issues and therefore because they
should have been aware they cannot be a
Bonafide purchaser is that what you're
saying um I'm saying that the in order
to be a Bonafide purchaser you must have
uh the you have all you have the
responsibility to know what you're
buying and and where the Authority for
that is the Authority for that uh was
listed in uh the filing from before uh
but where is it are you talking a
statute are you talking case law what
are you referring to uh case law and uh
case and statute um which statute so the
statute is uh is
15 uh or I'm sorry
55508 I think um which is says that has
to be a 5508 I believe um I'm pulling up
the
5508 I believe I'm pulling up what what
title what set
uh give me one second your honor code is
referred to you get a title like title
55 Dash something yes your honor um give
me one second I'm just pulling up my uh
the that specific
one uh
see okay
okay see
uh uh I'm sorry it was uh Idaho code uh
uh section
45-58 I believe that's the title
of
uh the title for you
uh see the title is uh 45 Lan mortgages
and and uh pledges chapter 15 trust
Deeds uh specifically uh
158 is finality of sale which uh says
that uh the purchaser must be uh in
favor of the purchaser in good faith for
Value um so the purchaser must be in
good faith uh and so that's the defining
part of the statute requires them to be
in good faith and then case law
uh for it
uh uh so
in uh one who relies for protection of
the doctrine of bonafide purchaser must
show that at the time of purchaser I'm
sorry Mr Bass I need you to read that
very slow much slower than you are oh
I'm sorry sorry about that uh so it's
says one who uh replies for protection
upon or who relies upon protection of
the doctrine of being a Bonafide
purchaser must show that at the time of
purchase he had paid a valuable cons uh
consideration upon and Upon A Brief a
belief and the validity of the vendor
claim that the title is without notice
actual or constructive of any
outstanding adverse rights of another
and that's Richard brick uh brick
Corporation versus is Herz Hardware uh I
I'm not sure how to read the actual
citation if if it's aw VA
476 uh it was listed in in my uh defense
or defendant bass's response to
plaintiff's motion for summary judgment
on page two uh
WV I'm sorry what is the citation a wva
uh citation is is Richard Banks
Corporation verse Hurst Hardware co uh
comma 80
wva
46 uh 476 Dash or I'm sorry comma
SE
685 so that's not from Idaho that sounds
like it's from West Virginia um and then
it goes comma uh colon Merchants trust
versus Davis comma 45 Idaho
uh
494 comma
29 uh
z uh P do
383 uh Merchants trust versus who uh
Merchant trust versus Davis Davis thank
you Davis that's 45 Idaho 494 45 uh 49
Idaho
494 49 Idaho 494 uh yes you
are uh and there's more behind it but is
that the Idaho one that you would like
or uh there's I just need to know that
there is an Idaho reference oh yes yes
your honor uh there is uh and then and
you're saying that that case law stands
for the fact that that a Bonafide
purchaser has to show that they paid
valuable consideration upon a reasonable
belief that they sell had had title that
the seller had uh had that the title was
free and clear of any issues uh at all
um that there was no no claims no uh uh
issues um it went further on to say that
further one who uh purchases Pro
property with sufficient knowledge uh to
put him and or a reasonable uh prudent
person on query is not a Bonafide by
and that is from free uh fman versus
Madden uh 13
Idaho uh
1138 um which is part of it uh so it's
if they have reason to uh to be on
notice which the trustees had notice
there was uh there was notice by me
being there saying that there was
problems at the auction um that there
was on the front of the house uh big uh
uh 2
by4 uh poster that that said there
there's issues with the that the
property was in contention um and post
it up visible for everyone to see um
it'd be unreasonable to think that you
would buy a property without even going
by and looking at it um which they would
be a see didn't you file a claim against
your prior mortgage company um I filed
to uh was dismissed it was dismissed for
uh in for ability to serve correctly I
wasn't dismissed with prejudice um I was
uh I was trying to find a lawyer to
continue the process um in the meantime
I was also trying to pay off the house
that they claimed that I owed in order
to take that off the table so that way I
didn't have them using that as leverage
uh against
me uh that that's when we enter so you
owed money on the house that they said
that doesn't mean that I it was legit it
was just that that's what they said and
they were using that to hold uh to to
try to work against me so you believe
that you've paid for that house in full
I believe that the house was paid off in
full and they agree what proof do you
have of that a letter of full
reconveyance to you to me yes your honor
from whom from uh Bank of
America and where's that in your in your
filings uh that was not in in the filing
uh that I gave uh in this part um it is
in uh it's in public record but it's ALS
uh it was from the case that was
dismissed uh but the other side
concurred that it was legit that it's
not in dispute um that the all right um
we've gone a far a field of what's that
issue in this case so you do not believe
that the uh that the plaintiff is a
bonafide purchaser because you believe
that you have stated that there were
issues with title all right anything
else in your argument well and they uh
they participated in price fixing by
calling the trustees that removes them
out from the statute uh or the
protection of of bonafied buyer by them
contacting them and and interacting with
them there's no uh there's no way for
they can say that it was just to get a
number but how much of the conversation
is is IR the fact that they called them
at all uh is what breaks the Sherman Act
all right we're going to have to move on
to Mr Nei now um because I have another
hearing that's supposed to start right
now but I want to hear from Mr Nei so uh
Mr Nei in regards to the argument that's
been made about Mr Pike as a potential
tenant of the property um I'd like to
hear your
argument thank you your honor and I'll
try to be as brief as as possible
because my my argument is set out in the
brief that I filed so I don't want to
repeat a lot I just want to stress the I
think what I think are the important
points uh the problem as I see it with
the plaintiff's case is that they're
seeking ejection ejectment against both
Mr Bass and Mr Pike and uh I've not
found any legal Authority in which a
tenant can be evicted through an
ejectment proceeding and the plaintiff
has not cited to any Authority in any of
its
briefs each of the named defendants Mr
Bass Mr Pike are in a different
relationship with the plaintiff as Mr
Stoddard acknowledged in his argument Mr
Bass the alleged former owner of the
real property uh therefore the case law
that I've read indicates that ejectment
would be the proper way to remove him
I'm not arguing in any way that he
should be removed I'm only stating that
ejectment would be the proper process
which is what the plaintiff is pursuing
however with regards to Mr Pike he is uh
or was a tenant of Mr Bass therefore
eviction is the proper method to seek
his removal from the property which is
something that the plaintiff has not
pled and has not done the the problem
for the plaintiff uh in its pleadings
and its arguments is that it seeks to
treat both Mr Bass and Mr Pike the same
even though each has a different
relationship to to the plaintiff um the
elements of ejectment are set out in
numerous cases uh issued by the Ido
Supreme Court first element is ownership
second is possession by the defendant
and the third is refusal by the
defendant to to surrender possession
those elements are set out in numerous
cases one of them cited by Mr Stoddard
is pro
indiviso 131 Idaho 7 41 that's a 1998
case however those three elements
presuppose that the defendant has
wrongfully refused to surrender
possession of the
property um uh they they therefore don't
apply to a tenant who has a valid lease
to the property as in this case
admittedly the Ido courts have confused
the terms eviction and ejectment and
generally in the number of cases I've
read have used those two terms
interchangeably so I recognize that it
is somewhat um confusing uh to
distinguish between the two doctrines
however the Ido Supreme Court has
expressly held that an ejectment action
not an eviction action is proper where
the possessor of real property remains
in possession after they lost ownership
through foreclosure
so the court did distinguish on at least
that one occasion and that's Indian
Springs LLC versus
Anderson 154 Idaho
708 and uh in that particular case the
plaintiff which would which would be
similar to the plaintiff in this case uh
filed an action for ejectment and then
amended its petition to add a claim for
eviction and the court found that it
ejectment claim was the proper vehicle
uh rather than eviction because as the
court said eviction statute Idaho code
6310 doesn't fit the facts of the case
they were seeking to remove an owner who
had been foreclosed upon and the court
said no this is an ejectment action not
an eviction receiving I've not found a
single case in which the court found
that an ejectment action is the proper
vehicle uh for removing a tenant such as
Mr Pike in this case where the
property's been foreclosed and the lease
holder continues in possession not found
a single case uh so I don't law
requires um that an eviction action be
initiated with regards to a tenant who
has uh a lease to property title six
chapter 3 those that that's where the
eviction statutes are located in Idaho
code and um and apparently the plaintiff
realized that it did not properly plead
in eviction action in this case because
it started arguing in its motion for in
its memorandum in support of its motion
that Mr Pike should be quote ejected for
non-payment of
rent no court has allowed that
the plaintiff argues in its reply brief
that it need and and these issues were
discussed in the brief that I filed on
behalf of Mr Pike and in its reply brief
the plaintiff argues that those strict
requirements of the eviction statute
6-33 pertaining to evictions for
non-payment of rent need not be complied
with because it's pursuing ejectment not
eviction and so I think in that sense uh
they're mixing up those terms but the
the Indian Springs LLC case issued by
the Supreme Court that I cited makes it
clear um that ejectment eviction is not
appropriate in an eviction action so the
O the the reverse would equally be true
that eviction would not be appropriate
if somebody's a lease holder and uh
that's the the best Authority that I can
find in the Ido Supreme Court decisions
that indicates that the plaintiff must
follow the eviction
statutes now the plaintiff cannot be
correct in arguing that it can seek
ejectment of Mr Pike and need not comply
with the eviction statutes because if it
is correct that means that all landlords
could use ejectment instead of eviction
where somebody's got a lease to property
and that certainly can't be correct and
there's no Authority for
it now with regards to um whether the
plaintiff is met its burden to show that
summary judgment is appropriate in this
case it attacks Mr Pikes affidavit
arguing that when he when Mr Pike says
it he's paid his rent he's current on
his rent he paid this much who we paid
it to he sets out all those
facts the the plaintiff argues that's a
conclusory statement but I'm sure the
court is aware that when uh when the
statutes uh pertaining to where the
rules pertaining to summary judgment uh
say that you can't use conclusory
statements that's talking about legally
conclusory not factually inclusory Mr
Pike has set out the facts that he has a
lease he's in compliance with that lease
he's paid the rent who he's paid it to
how much he has paid um those are
factual statements and those are in the
record and uh summary judgment ought not
be issued in this proceeding given that
there is a legitimate dispute of facts
in this
proceeding um your honor uh plti also
false Mr Pike for continuing to pay his
rent to Mr Bass and that's the most
curious argument that the plaintiff
makes
because as Mr Stoddard has stated and as
the plaintiff has attached to its
petition the plaintiff sent a notice of
eviction and three-day demand the
property and your honor that uh that
notice is in the record it's attached to
the petition and it specifically States
if you believe you are a Bonafide tenant
with an unexpired lease or a Bonafide
tenant with an expired lease you are
required to make your required monthly
lease payments during the remainder of
your lease agreement and I talked about
this in my brief your honor uh Mr Pike
did that
he did exactly what the plaintiff stated
but Mr Stoddard seems to think there's
other instructions in there that told Mr
Pike what to do there aren't your honor
so it's curious when Mr started argued
at the start of this hearing that he
said that um that Mr Pike was told in
that notice to pay the rent to the new
owners he was never told that here onor
so so Mr Pike did what he was told to do
he remained in compliance of the lease
he continued to pay his rent to Mr Bass
which he was legally obligated to do
under that lease agreement so I think
that Mr Stoddard's argument Falls uh
flat your honor um on the fifth page of
the plaintiff's reply Reef uh the
plaintiff refers to that provision and
Mr Pike's Reliance on it the the
plaintiff writes quote that Mr Pike
relied quote on a singular sentence from
the notice to vacate that he received
and disregards the remainder of the
notice well your honor the plaintiff
ignores the fact that that quote
singular sentence was the only
instructions to Mr Pike contained in the
notice so Mr Pike did what he was
required to do and of course that
argument begs the question what else
would the plaintiff have had Mr Pike do
when he was relying on the clear
directive in the notice so youor uh it
it's
odd
that the plaintiff directs Mr Pike to
stay current on the lease with no other
instructions and then fults him for
doing that um your honor it's noteworthy
that the plaintiff's petition does not
State a factual basis upon which Mr Pike
can be either ejected or evicted the
word eviction or evict
does not appear in the plaintiff's
petition they have not properly pled
their case the rules are clear the
statutes are clear the eviction statutes
require a three-day notice if the
plaintiff is now arguing which they
never they did not plead in their petion
that Mr Pike is behind on the rent
they've only argue that in their
memorandum and supported their memor
motion for summary judgment they've not
given the required three-day notice
putting Mr Pike on notice that he's
behind on the rent uh which would then
allow him to cure if in fact he was
though that is a dispute a fact whether
he is behind on the rent or not so your
honor these facts are set out in the act
of
David there is clearly a dispute of fact
in this and um uh the plaintiff has
acknowledged that if the lease is in
effect and Mr Pike is in compliance Mr
Pike is protected by the f Federal
protecting tenants at foreclosure act uh
so that federal statute protects Mr Pike
and um therefore given this dispute of
fact summary judgment would not be
proper should be denied thank you your
Mr n have one question in the lease on
page five of the lease top of the
page uh condition 32.2 if the property
is sold the the lease will transfer with
the property and the new owner will be
bound by all the terms and conditions of
this lease why did Mr Pike not pay the
new owner his lease agreement because
your honor Mr Pike was aware that the
ownership of the property was in dispute
and he was concerned that if he did not
pay Mr Pike he would be in violation of
that lease and so um where Mr Pike
receives clear directive from the uh the
alleged new owner of the property to
remain in compliance with the lease Mr
Pike believed in good faith that he had
to continue to pay the rent to Mr Pike
to Mr sorry and um and so uh as I stated
in my brief if the plaintiff uh believed
that that was improper it should have a
petitioned to amend its complaint to um
seek eviction against Mr Pike or um to
obtain reimbursement of those rents paid
to Mr Bass from Mr Bass and um uh the
plaintiff has not done that once the
plaintiff was put on notice that uh
there was a valid lease in effect uh it
did not seek to um uh obtain the rental
payments from Mr bats uh and instead it
just simply argues that Mr pipe didn't
do what he was supposed to do and to be
clear the first notice plaintiff had of
lease was on August 14th when you filed
your
answer uh well your honor um Mr stod uh
did state in his Abid davit he filed
three or declarations um and uh they
indicated that there was a conversation
before I was involved between Mr Pike
and I believe it was Mr stod uh
regarding whether there was a lease and
uh Mr Pike stated that he had a lease uh
there's a dispute as for whether there
it's was a month-to-month lease or a
written lease and um but Mr Pike is not
an attorney he doesn't didn't know what
to do and as soon as he contacted me um
I began communicating with Mr Stoddard
and provided Mr stter with a copy of
that leeks so we did that as quickly as
possible but we're dealing with an
unsophisticated party here your honor um
however there's no no statute no legal
Authority that I can find that required
m Mr uh Pike to provide that lease to
the
plaintiff um the protecting tendance in
forclosure act simply states that if
there is a valid lease he's
protected all right thank
you um Mr Stoddard um it's your motion
I'll give you the last
word thank you honor I'll keep my
comments brief with respect to M Mr
bass's argument
there's nothing in the record indicating
any instructions from a County
prosecutor any open cases and so that's
just an again an UNS unsupported
conclusory allegation um with respect to
bonified purchaser status again your
honor the idol code um delineates a
difference between
um a Bonafide purchaser for value and
anybody buying at the sale uh the
trustees deed is afforded Prima
presumption of compliance to everyone if
you're a Bonafide purchaser for Value
it's
conclusive uh in the reply brief we
noted that that dispute that Mr Bass
wants to argue about is ultimately
immaterial because there is nothing in
the court record indicating any failure
to comply with the Idaho trustees
act so whether it's primacia and can be
rebutted or it's conclusive and can't be
rebutted
where there's no evidence one way or the
other indicating that it wasn't complied
with and all of the evidence shows it
was complied with um that's an elusory
argument um and and so for that reason
um Mr bass's arguments fail
Additionally the citation to uh the
Appel case notes that Bonafide purchaser
status relies upon notice of statutory
irregularities in the non-judicial
Foreclosure sale
that's what Bonafide purchaser and
status and inquiry notice is limited to
not did I put a paper in my window
saying I disagree uh this shouldn't go
to foreclosure haha nobody can ever be a
Bonafide purchase I object against that
the record before the court contains the
land record of I object against that
which contains the of trust contains the
notice of default contains the statutory
required uh notices under the trustees
act all of which were reported uh the
notice of the postponement again all of
which were reported uh and a trustees de
conveying ownership to to my client um
as such they were entitled to possession
10 days
after uh with respect to Mr Pike again
your honor I I think the simplest
classification of of the response is the
dog ate my
homework I paid the wrong person and now
Mr naggie wants me wants my client to
have to go to the person that he paid
erroneously that's not the contractual
relationship that Mr Nagi wants and Mr
Pike are seeking to enforce this was an
action for
ejectment uh against an individual
occupying the
property uh he submitted a lease and
assert that affirmative defense that my
client is required to honor that lease
agreement the burden of proof on an
affirmative defense is Mr Pike if he
wants my client to honor the lease
agreement and he needs to prove that
he's in compliance with that lease
agreement he admits he is not he did not
make payments to my client he is not
making payments to my client um he has
not sto the discour those payments from
Mr B uh and so um there is no question
of fact with respect to that really what
we're looking at as a technical argument
that Mr ngi believes that the only
recourse against Mr Pike is that of an
unlawful container action um I've been
doing this it's a long
time courts have have applied both
ejectment uh and I use it in the context
of a post forclosure uh eviction um
because it's never clear under what
Authority or what right a person
occupying a property is uh he could have
been a squatter for all I know uh that's
why we sent a notice to vacate that
informs them here's the new owner if
you're there under a lease send the new
owner your lease if you think you're Ed
send the new owner proof of that and
more importantly
pay um the notice of vacates very clear
uh in order for us to determine on
behalf of the property owner the new
owner what your rights you may have
under the protecting attendance
foreclosure act you must do the
following Mr Pike didn't do any moves
down to the next paragraph if you're
determined to be a Bonafide tenant with
an expired lease the property owns owner
the new owner identified in the previous
paragraph provides notice that your
right to remain in the property expires
no later than 90 calendar days and then
the next paragraph tells them if you're
there in an unexpired lease you need to
make rent payments Mr Nei wants to
extract one paragraph and say well we
complied with that but you know don't
pay attention to the rest the letter
read in its entirety informed Mr Pike
that the property was foreclosed
that there is a new owner that he has
protections under the protecting tenants
at foreclosure act but in order to
evaluate that in order to determine what
those protections might be here's what
you need to do he did not do any of
those and instead wants to argue well I
just kept doing what I was doing before
I kept paying the old owner Mr Bass uh
even though I was informed that a
property went to sale you know maybe I
was legally mistaken those those
ultimately aren't offensive um
uh lastly your honor with respect to the
unlawful detainer act if if that's the
way Mr Navy wants to go Ido code section
6-
315 provide that when the evidence that
a defendant is guilty of un off of
container for grounds not PL in the
complaint is
presented the quote the judge must order
that such complaint be forth with
amended to conform with such proofs
without any imposition of terms no
continuance shall be permitted upon
account for such amendments unless the
defendant by affidavit files shows to
the satisfaction of the Court good cause
therefore the purpose of that statutory
provision is similar to this um I'm
trying to an evict a tenant on ground a
but turns out when we get to trial
ground a is on a legal basis but he's
also in violation for other grounds the
unlawful detainer action was meant for
expedited proceedings to
occupants uh we did not proceed under
the unlawful container act again because
this is in a for poost foreclosure
eviction action that to the Benefit of
Mr Bass and Mr Pike has afforded them
seven months of continued occupation of
this property as opposed to 14
days which is how quickly unlawful
container action could have been for
student presented so um at the end of
the day just to summarize real quickly
um for your honor Mr Bass is not
entitled continued possession of the
property his interest in the property
was terminated as a result of the
trustee sale there's been no showing of
any statutory or procedural irregularity
or non-compliance with the trustees act
Mr Pike he wants to occupy the property
pursuant to a lease he needs to prove
his compliance with the lease he admits
he is not uh the fact that he made a
legal mistake as to who he should pay
does not create an issue of material
fact that he has not paid continues to
not pay my client and therefore is not
in compliance with the lease and as such
we seek checkman uh to have both of
those individuals removed from the
property uh so that my client can take
possession thank
you all right uh thank you all um
Court's going to take this matter under
advisement and I'm going to R issue a
written decision in due course um I will
try
to I can't give you date on when that
will be issued but I'll try to get that
out when I can anything further on this
matter today not nothing further your
honor thank you for your time I believe
I not allowed to say anything else so
thank you your
honor right um we don't have anything
else said in this matter at this time um
depending on the outcome of my decision
um if I deny the motion for summary
judgment on either party will set this
matter for a status conference at that
point or a scheduling
conference all right with that um have a
great day we'll see you uh see you all
again thank you your honor thank you
we'll be in
recess
[__] for
today
is
2024 10th October uh 22 and it is now
1056 a.m. Pacific Standard time I'm
Jeremy Bass through 1782 that was the
court hearing with honorable Judge Evans
and so uh other parties already named